Hi, this is Matt Baker. This video is a
compilation of six episodes I did on
this channel about the historical Jesus,
with each one introducing a hypothesis
about who Jesus might really have been.
The first five are not taken too
seriously by most mainstream historians,
but they're a lot of fun. And by
explaining them, it allowed me to
introduce a lot of the historical
context related to Jesus, such as who
the main leaders of first century Judea
were, what other events were happening
at the time, and which extra biblical
sources include references to Jesus.
However, at the end, I do present the
hypothesis preferred by most secular
historians. Now, keep in mind that the
goal of the whole thing is not to try
and debunk Christian beliefs or to try
and convince anyone that the final
hypothesis is the correct one. I simply
want to present to you a bunch of
different viewpoints because, like I
say, it's a good way to learn a bit of
history. So, if hearing other viewpoints
is something you're open to, enjoy.
I'm going to start with a hypothesis
which claims that Jesus was a secret
grandson of Herod. Personally, it's not
the hypothesis that I think is the most
likely to be true, but it's definitely
the one that I most want to be true
because it's basically the equivalent of
a good old useful charts who would be
king episode. It was developed by a
lawyer named Joseph Raymond and
presented in his book, The Herodian
Messiah Case for Jesus as grandson of
Herod. In order to explain why this
hypothesis is a possibility, I first
need to give you some genealogical
information relating to the time period
in which Jesus lived. To do this, I'm
going to be using my biblical family
tree chart, which like all of our charts
is available from our website,
usefulcharts.com.
You're probably familiar with the
Mcabes, who are the heroes of the Kaneka
story. They led a revolt against the
Greeks who had desecrated the Jewish
temple. After their victory, the Mcabes
were able to rededicate the temple and
set up an independent Jewish kingdom,
which historians refer to as the
Hasminian Kingdom. Hasminian being the
official family name of the Mcabes.
Several generations of Hasminians ruled
this kingdom, serving as both high
priests and monarchs until the 60s B.CE.
when there was a civil war between two
brothers, Herkinus II and Aristobulus
II. At this point, the Romans stepped in
and helped put an end to the conflict,
but in the process, they also took
control of Judea and made it a client
state of Rome. Initially, they allowed
the Hasminians to stay on as monarchs.
But when the Hasminian king Antiggonus
II betrayed them, allying instead with
the Parththeians, the Romans sent a
general named Herod to reconquer Judea,
which he did. At this point, Antiggonus
II was taken to Rome and beheaded by
none other than Mark Anthony. And in his
place, Herod was instead made king of
the Jews, becoming known as Herod the
Great. Initially the high priesthood was
passed to Antigonus II's nephew
Aristobulus III but soon thereafter it
became an appointed position instead.
Thus the Hasminian dynasty came to an
end or did it? Next I want to introduce
you to Herod's family. This chart only
shows three of his sons because it is
these three who are most important to
the biblical story. Archelaus because he
became ruler of Judea after his father's
death. Antipus because he became ruler
of Galilee which is where Jesus was
from. And Aristobulus IV because he was
the father of the later king Herod
Agrippa. Note that Aristobulus IV was
given a Hasminian name because his
mother was a Hasminian princess being
the sister of the last Hasminian high
priest Aristobulus III. Finally, take
note that between the reigns of Herod
Archelaus and Herod Agria I there was a
period of about 35 years when there was
no Herodian ruler in Judea and instead
the area was ruled directly by Roman
governors such as Pontius Pilate. But
here's the thing, Herod actually had
several more sons. For example,
Aristobulus IV had an older full brother
named Alexander. The two of them were
his second and thirdborn sons. And then
there was his fourthborn, Herod II, who
was the son of Herod the Great's third
wife. But the most important missing son
is his firstborn, Antipedater, who was
the son of Herod's first wife, Doris.
The reason why he's not included on the
poster is that he died before Herod and
thus is not mentioned in the Bible. Now,
if you know anything about Herod, it's
probably that he was super crazy and
loved killing people, even children. For
example, when Herod became king, he made
sure to kill almost all of the remaining
Hasminans, even the babies, so that he
wouldn't have any rivals, which is
likely what inspired the massacre of the
innocence legend found in the Gospels.
According to Josephus, Herod allowed
only five Hasminans to escape the
initial purge. Mary Amnney, whom he
married, but then later killed. Mary's
brother, Aristobulus III, who he later
killed. Mary's mother, Alexandra, who he
later killed. Mary's grandfather,
Herkinus II, who he later killed. And
finally, an unnamed daughter of
Antigonus II, who as far as we know, he
did not kill. We're going to come back
to her. Now, lest you think that Herod
only liked to kill other people's
children, I have to inform you that he
killed several of his own as well. For
example, near the end of his life in 7
B.CE, he became convinced that Alexander
and Aristobulus IV were plotting to kill
him. So he had them both executed on
charges of treason. Then in 4 BC, just a
few months before he himself died, he
became convinced that his firstborn son,
Antipeder, was going to kill him. So he
had him executed, too. On top of this,
Herod II's mother was claimed to be in
on the plot. So Herod II was removed
from the line of succession, even though
his life was spared. This meant that
Archelaus, Herod's fifthborn son, was
now his primary heir, which is why
Archelaus ended up inheriting Judea
after Herod's death, as mentioned in
Matthew 222.
But this is where things get
interesting. What if Antipedater had a
secret son? If he did, that individual
would have had an excellent claim to the
throne. To find out if this was even
possible, we first have to find out
whether or not Antipeder had any wives.
Well, according to Josephus, he had two.
One was a daughter of Aristobulus IVth.
But the other, very interestingly, was
that unnamed Hasminian princess that I
mentioned earlier. Remember, she was the
daughter of the very last Hasminian
king. And as far as we know, by 4 B.CE,
CE, she would have been the last
remaining Hasminian to still be alive.
Which brings up the question, why was
she allowed to survive? Well, probably
because Herod wanted his firstborn son,
Antipator, to have a Hasminian wife like
he initially did in order to better
cement their dynasty's claim to power.
Although of course we know that in the
end Herod ended up killing Antipator.
But there's no record of him killing
Antipator's wife or any of their
children. Presumably they didn't have
any. But what if Antipator's wife was
pregnant in 4 B.CE? And what if the baby
was born after both Antipator and Herod
the Great died? That child would have
had a double claim to the throne as both
the seniormost grandson of Herod the
Great and the only male descendant of
the last Hasminian king. Okay, by this
point I think you already know where I'm
going. What if Jesus, who was also born
in 4 B.CE, was this hypothetical baby?
And what if Mary was Antipator's widow,
the last member of the Hasminian
dynasty? Several of the details fit,
especially the timing. Also, the fact
that Mary was a single woman, pregnant
with a fatherless baby who ended up
marrying someone who was not the father
of the baby. On top of this, we know
that Mary, Joseph, and the baby ended up
fleeing to Egypt, specifically to escape
the wrath of Herod the Great, and that
when they returned home after Herod's
death, they opted to hide out in Galilee
after hearing that Archelaus had been
made ruler. Think about it. It's
actually much easier to believe that
Jesus must have been some sort of
special baby that Herod wanted dead for
political reasons than to believe that
he was a miracle child born of a virgin.
However, all of these aligning details
are not actually the primary foundation
upon which Joseph Raymond developed his
hypothesis. His main line of evidence is
actually based on Jesus's genealogy as
given in the Gospel of Luke. According
to most scholars, the Gospel of Matthew
provides us with Jesus's legal ancestry
through his adopted father, Joseph.
Whereas the Gospel of Luke provides us
with his biological ancestry through his
mother, Mary. So let's now look at the
names of Mary's ancestors given in Luke.
In particular, the last seven names
prior to Mary's generation.
Interestingly, the second to last name
is Mat, which is short for Matathias, or
in English, Matthew. Well, what do you
know? The Hebrew name of Antigonus II
was none other than Matthew. Above him,
we get Levi and Melhe. Well, Melhe is
simply the Hebrew name for king, and
Levi is another word for priest. So
perhaps these two names were actually
inserted as a kind of secret code
indicating that Jesus descended from the
Hasminians who were the only family in
all of Jewish history to serve as both
kings and priests. Next above Melhei we
get Jennai which is short for Janus an
extremely rare Jewish name. In fact the
only known Janaeas in this entire period
was are you ready for it? the Hasminian
king Alexander Janius, grandfather of
Antagonist II. Finally, we get one more
very important Hasminian name, another
Matathias. You see, if we keep going
back from Alexander Janias, we
eventually come to Matathias, the father
of the Mcabes and the initial leader of
the Makabian revolt. But what about
Joseph and Heli? Well, Raymon doesn't
really offer an explanation for Joseph
except to say that that name and all the
rest above Matathias were probably just
filler. However, for Heli, he suggests
that this individual was perhaps the
adopted father of Mary, who took care of
her after Antigonus II was killed. After
all, she was likely a baby at the time,
and therefore, her adopted father would
have played a major role in her life. As
an aside, take note that Catholic
tradition says that Mary's father was a
priest named Joakim, which actually fits
because an alternative name for Joakim
was Eliakim, or for short, Heli. Also,
it makes sense that an orphaned
Hasminian princess would have been put
in the care of a high-ranking priestly
family, considering that the Hasminians
had been not only royalty, but also
priests. Speaking of names, there are a
few ancient sources that mention that
Jesus's real father was a Roman soldier
named Panta. Interestingly, Panta sounds
an awful lot like Antipedater. And
Antipeder was known to have served in
the Roman army during his many years
living in Rome. Probably a coincidence,
but a kind of tantalizing one. Okay. The
final thing that fits with this
hypothesis is the trial and execution of
Jesus. He is first brought before the
Jewish authorities who try to charge him
with breaking basic religious rules and
with claiming to be the Messiah.
However, next when he is brought before
the Roman governor Pontius Pilate,
Pilate asks him just one thing and this
one question is recorded in all four
gospels. Pilate looks at Jesus and asks,
"Are you the king of the Jews?" That is
pretty direct and pretty specific. Not
really something you'd ask of a simple
troublemaker unless they actually did
have a legitimate claim to the title.
Now remember, according to the biblical
account, the Jewish authorities hadn't
said anything about him claiming to be
an actual king. They charged him with
claiming to be the Messiah. To a modern
Christian mind, the difference between
Messiah and earthly king is a big one.
But to a first century Jewish mind, it
was not. You see, in Hebrew, the word
Messiah or Messiah literally means the
anointed one and was exclusively used in
an earthly sense for individuals who
were or would be anointed as either king
or priest. So for Pilate to go from
Messiah to king was not actually much of
a leap. Okay, so that's the hypothesis.
In many ways, it makes a lot of sense.
However, if you're familiar with the New
Testament, you will have noticed at
least one major flaw. In scripture,
Jesus is quite clearly expected to be a
descendant of King David, not of the
Herodians or Hasminans. So, how does
Joseph Raymond, the main proponent of
the hypothesis, deal with this problem?
Well, he offers two potential solutions.
One is the suggestion that Jesus was a
descendant of David through Antipator's
mother, Doris. Doris was Herod's first
wife and the only one to be like Herod
himself, an Idmian or Edomite. You see,
Edom was a kingdom [clears throat] south
of Judea. And Doris was a member of that
kingdom's royal family, which may have
intermarried with Judahite royalty way
back when the House of David dynasty was
in power. The second possible solution
is that while the people expected the
Messiah to be from the Davidic line,
Jesus himself hinted that he was not.
Perhaps because he felt that being a
combined king priest from the Hasminian
family was even better. There's a rarely
discussed passage that shows up in all
three synoptic gospels, which is the
only time that Jesus himself addresses
the idea that the Messiah had to be from
the line of David. In Mark's version,
Jesus says, "How can the scribes say
that the Messiah is the son of David?
David himself by the Holy Spirit
declared, "The Lord," meaning the
Messiah, "Said to my Lord," meaning
David, "Sit at my right hand until I put
your enemies under your feet." David
himself calls him the Messiah, Lord. So,
how can he, the Messiah, be his David's
son?
In episode 1, we explored the
possibility that Jesus was a grandson of
Herod the Great as well as a descendant
of the Hasminians. Well, in today's
video, we're going to explore a
different hypothesis. One in which Jesus
was actually the leader of a major
insurrection and the exact same person
that Josephus refers to as the Egyptian.
But first, let me clear something up.
The goal of this series is not to debate
whether or not Jesus was or is divine.
My assumption is that you've already
made up your mind about that issue one
way or the other. My goal
[clears throat] is simply to explore
some fun ideas about who Jesus might
have been as a historical person for
those of us who have already come to the
conclusion that he was a mere man.
However, this doesn't mean that there's
nothing of value in this series for
committed Christians. Along the way,
I'll be presenting a lot of real world
information about the time period in
which Jesus lived. So, as long as you
don't mind hearing alternative
viewpoints, go ahead and keep watching.
In episode 1, we mostly focused on the
Herodian and Hasminian family trees.
Well, in episode two, we'll be focusing
more on the general timeline of events.
This is because if Jesus was the guy
that Josephus calls the Egyptian, it's
going to require a shift in time, which
happens to be the name of the book that
this episode is based on. A shift in
time was written by Lena Einhorn, who is
a medical doctor and film director from
Sweden. So, let's take a look at the
timeline of Judean history around the
time of Jesus. First, let's place the
local rulers on the chart. As we
discussed last time, Herod the Great
ruled Judea from 37 B.CE. to his death
in 4 B.CE, CE at which time he was
succeeded in Judea by his son Herod
Archelaus. Archelaus then reigned until
6 CE which is when the Romans who were
the real rulers decided to make Judea an
official province and replaced the
Jewish monarchy with Roman governors.
The first seven governors were Caponius,
Ambivilus, Rufus, Gatus, Pontius Pilate,
Marcellus and Morillis. Of these seven
names, it's likely that only one stands
out to you. That would be Pontius Pilate
because according to the New Testament
and several other sources, he was the
governor when Jesus was killed. We'll
come back to that event in a moment, but
for now, let's continue on with the
rulers. In 41 CE, the monarchy in Judea
was briefly reinstated with Herod Agria,
a grandson of Herod the Great, being
made king. But his reign did not last
long because in 44 CE he suddenly
dropped dead probably from being
poisoned. An event that the Bible
actually records in Acts 21 21-23. After
agria it was back to governors. The most
notable being Felix who ruled the
longest and is mentioned several times
in the Bible in connection to Paul's
arrest and trial. Now in addition to the
local rulers, let me also add the Roman
emperors to the chart. The first of
course was Augustus who was the adopted
son of Julius Caesar. He reigned from 27
B.CE to 14 CE and was then followed by
Tiberius from 14 to 37, Caligula from 37
to 41, Claudius from 41 to 54, and Nero
from 54 to 68. With Nero's death, the
dynasty that had started with Julius
Caesar came to an end and civil war
broke out, resulting in 69 CE being the
year of four emperors. In the end, a
general named Vespasian was victorious,
and he was able to establish a new
dynasty known as the Flavians.
Next, let's add Jesus to the timeline.
According to the Gospel of Matthew,
Jesus was born sometime around Herod the
Great's death in 4 B.CE. However,
according to the Gospel of Luke, he was
born at the time of a census associated
with a Syrian governor named Quirinius.
We know that that census took place in 6
CE because that was the year that the
Romans deposed Herod Archelaus.
Basically, before appointing Caponius,
they sent in Quirinius from the next
door province of Syria to calculate how
much tax they could get from their new
province of Judea. This is really
important because it sparked a major
Jewish rebellion led by a man known as
Judas of Galilee. We'll be talking more
about him in episode 3, but for now,
just take note that Luke associates the
birth of Jesus with the rebellion of 6
CE. Now, one of the most helpful bits of
chronological information given in the
entire New Testament can be found in
Luke 3:1. It starts off with in the 15th
year of the reign of Tiberius Caesar.
This is very helpful because we know
that Tiberius's 15th year was 28 CE.
Luke then goes on to talk about John the
Baptist starting his ministry in that
year and then Jesus starting his soon
thereafter. We thus have an earliest
possible start date for Jesus becoming a
public figure. As for when Jesus died,
most scholars place that event in either
30 or 33 CE. So according to the Bible,
this window here of 5 years represents
when all the main events in Jesus's life
took place. Okay, there's one last thing
I want to put on this timeline. unrest,
meaning times when Jewish rebel activity
was high. I've already mentioned the
rebellion of 6 CE. That was actually the
culmination of many years of unrest that
had been building ever since the
Herodians took over. But the rebellion
of 6CE was quashed by the Romans so
successfully that things went quiet for
the next several decades. In fact, in
describing Judea during those decades,
the famous Roman historian Tacitus said,
"Under Tiberius, all was quiet." But
then starting with the death of Agria,
which was during the reign of Claudius,
things got noisy once again. In fact,
from this point onwards, the unrest kept
building and eventually resulted in the
first Jewish Roman war, which began in '
66 and culminated in the complete
destruction of Jerusalem and its temple
in the year 70. And guess who was the
Roman general in charge of Roman troops
during that war? None other than
Vespasian, who ended up becoming the
emperor. Okay, now that I've set the
scene, let me introduce you to the main
argument from Lena Einhorn's book, A
Shift in Time. Basically, Einhorn argues
that Jesus could not have been active
from 28 to 33 CE because the Gospels are
full of references to rebel activity,
even though we know that there were no
rebels active in Judea during the reign
of Tiberius. Let me give you some
specifics.
First, there's the crucifixion itself.
As you might know, images of the
crucifixion usually contain not one but
three crosses. That's because according
to the gospels, Jesus was hung between
two thieves or robbers. The Greek word
for thief here is lest which could be
more accurately translated as a rebel or
revolutionary. You see, a lesty was not
just a simple thief, but rather a thief
who stole in order to support a
rebellion. Then there's Barabus, the guy
who Pilate released instead of Jesus.
According to Mark 15:7, Barabbus was in
prison with the insurrectionists who had
committed murder during the
insurrection. What insurrection? This
was supposedly 30 or 33 CE, and there
hadn't been any insurrections in
Jerusalem since 6 CE. Einhorn went as
far as to count every reference to the
word robber or rebel in Josephus and
made this chart from her findings. As
you can see, Josephus uses the word
rebel many times before 6 CE and many
times after 44 CE, but zero times,
that's right, zero times between 6 and
44. But wait, there's more. In John
18:12, Jesus is arrested on the Mount of
Olives. It says, "The soldiers, their
officer, and the Jewish police arrested
Jesus and bound him." The Greek word for
soldiers there is spir, which refers to
a unit with at least 600 soldiers. And
the Greek word for officer is kilaros,
which literally means commander of a
thousand. So even though Jesus
supposedly had only 11 disciples with
him at that point, the leader sent 600
to a,000 soldiers to capture him. This
might be an indication that in the real
version of events, Jesus might have been
on the Mount of Olives with a much
larger group of followers. And he might
not have been just waiting around and
praying. Maybe in the real version, he
was planning an attack on the city of
Jerusalem, which was then thwarted by
the Romans. Now, lest you think that's
crazy, let me show you some more hints
from the Bible itself that point towards
insurrection. In Luke 22:36,
as they are about to go to the Mount of
Olives, Jesus tells his disciples to get
ready. He says, "The one who has a purse
must take it, and likewise a bag, and
the one who has no sword must sell his
cloak and buy one." So, here's Jesus
literally telling people to bring
swords. And we know that they did
because later Peter uses a sword to cut
off someone's ear. Even the names of the
disciples point to rebellion. For
example, Peter is also known as Simon
Beriona. Bariona is usually interpreted
as being two words bar Jonah meaning son
of Jonah but as a single word which it
is bariona actually means rebel or
insurrectionist
then there's James and John called the
sons of thunder the Greek word for
thunder there is most commonly used to
refer to rebellion so really it's James
and John the sons of rebellion there's
also Simon the Zealot. The Zealots
definitely being a major Jewish rebel
group and Judas a Scariot. A scariot
meaning one who carries a dagger.
Einhorn gives many more examples in her
book of how the details in the New
Testament point to a more rebellious
time period. For now, I want to jump to
her solution. While the characters and
events in the gospels do not fit with
what we know about the 20s and 30s CE,
they fit perfectly with what we know of
the 40s and 50s. In other words, if we
just shift everything by about 20 years,
it all makes sense, especially the part
about the story coming to a climax on
the Mount of Olives. Which brings me to
the individual that Josephus calls the
Egyptian. In antiquities of the Jews
book 208, Josephus tells us about the
death of Emperor Claudius and the start
of the reign of Nero. So that puts us
around the year 54 or 55 CE. He then
writes, "Moreover, there came out of
Egypt about this time to Jerusalem one
that said he was a prophet and advised
the multitude of the common people to go
along with him to the Mount of Olives,
as it was called, which lay over against
the city, and at a distance of five
furlongs." He said farther that he would
show them from hence how at his command
the walls of Jerusalem would fall down.
and he promised them that he would
procure them an entrance into the city
through those walls when they were
fallen down. Now, when Felix was
informed of these things, he ordered his
soldiers to take their weapons and came
against them with a great number of
horsemen and footmen from Jerusalem and
attacked the Egyptian and the people
that were with him. He also slew 400 of
them and took 200 alive, but the
Egyptian himself escaped out of the
fight. but did not appear anymore. Now,
here's the really interesting thing.
This guy, who we simply know as the
Egyptian, also shows up, albeit very
briefly, in the New Testament. In Acts
21, Paul, arguably the most important
leader of the early Christian movement,
gets arrested in Jerusalem. In verse 38,
we read that the first thing that the
Roman official says to him is, "Aren't
you one of the followers of Jesus, the
man we crucified two decades ago?"
Actually, no. That's not what it says.
What he says is, "Are you not the
Egyptian who recently stirred up a
revolt and led the 4,000 assassins out
into the wilderness?" In other words,
the official confuses Paul with the
figure called the Egyptian and assumes
that Paul must be involved in that
movement. Now, I want you to notice four
elements in this verse. Egypt, the
number 4,000, assassins, and the
wilderness. First off, the word
assassin. The Greek word here is sakari,
which was a type of Jewish rebel,
perhaps a subset of the Zealots who
carried a small sword or dagger under
their cloak. Very reminiscent of the
disciples on the Mount of Olives.
Second, there's the mention of the
wilderness. We know for certain that
Jesus spent a lot of time in the
wilderness, and this was often where he
would teach and draw crowds. Third, the
number 4,000 is interesting because it
also shows up in connection to Jesus
being the number of people he fed with
seven loaves of bread and a few small
fish. Finally, there's Egypt. That's the
one piece that doesn't fit, right? After
all, Jesus was from Galilee, not Egypt.
So, why would anyone refer to him as the
Egyptian? Well, remember the Gospel of
Matthew says that after Jesus was born,
his family fled to Egypt. We also have
very little information about the first
30 years of his life. So maybe the
family actually stayed in Egypt longer
than is thought. After all, there was a
large Jewish community there. Another
possible source for the Egyptian/Jesus
is the Talmud. It has long been
speculated that a figure mentioned there
by the name of Ben Stada might actually
be a reference to Jesus. In Shabbat 104b
verse 5, it says, "Didn't the infamous
Benada take magic spells out of Egypt in
a scratch on his flesh?" It then goes on
to explain how stada means to stray and
that this is a reference to his mother
Mary who had him out of wedlock with a
man named Panta. So, if this is indeed a
reference to Jesus, it's evidence that
people may have thought that his
miracles were based on things he had
learned in Egypt. Now, none of these
points are knockown arguments that prove
that Jesus and the Egyptian were one and
the same, but there are enough
similarities that when taken together
with the time shift, make it at least a
possibility worth considering. Here's
how it would work. Let's say that Jesus
was born in Judea but then taken to
Egypt by his parents where he grew up
and eventually learned to do some magic.
Now, whether this was just illusion
designed to trick people or whether he
actually believed he was using some sort
of ancient Egyptian knowledge doesn't
really matter because either way,
sometime in the 50s CE, he ended up back
in Judea where he then used this magic
to perform miracles and draw crowds. He
also gave his opinions about religion
and philosophy and eventually felt that
he had a big enough following that he
could try and take the city of Jerusalem
by force becoming the Messiah or
anointed one that would then rule Judea
independently of the Romans. But he
failed and somehow escaped crucifixion.
Although there was perhaps some doubt
over whether or not he was in fact
killed, which might explain the
resurrection appearances as well as the
Barabus story, the one in which Barabus
is set free and Jesus is crucified. It's
long been noted that the name Barabus
literally means son of the father,
meaning that Jesus and Barabus might
actually have been the same person and
that the original source material simply
chose to give us two possible endings to
the story. Kind of like a choose your
own adventure book. Finally, over time,
it's possible that the idea of Jesus,
aka the Egyptian, being a physical
Messiah, morphed into the idea that he
was instead more of a spiritual Messiah.
Particularly after 70 CE when Jerusalem
was destroyed and all hope of a physical
victory was lost. That's when his
comment on the Mount of Olives about the
walls coming down went from being
something he had planned to do at that
very moment to a prophecy he made about
the future. Interestingly, it was around
70 CE that the earliest gospels were
written. Perhaps it was at that point
that the writers decided to shift the
events to an earlier, more peaceful time
so that the focus could be more on
Jesus's spiritual teachings rather than
on his insurrection. All they had to do
was switch Felix to Pontius Pilate and
work in a mention of Emperor Tiberius, a
change that was then copied by future
historians such as Tacitus. The main
problem with shifting the gospels
timeline 20 years into the future is
that it puts Jesus's death after the
earliest Pauline epistles. Even secular
historians agree that at least seven of
the New Testament books attributed to
Paul are in fact genuine with the
earliest one Galatians usually being
dated to around 48 CE. However,
according to Josephus, the revolt led by
the Egyptian took place in 54 CE.
Therefore, if Jesus and the Egyptian
were the same person, how could Paul be
writing about Jesus's death 6 years
earlier? Now, Lena Einhorn does in fact
address this issue in her book. She
points out that the bulk of Paul's
ministry can actually be squeezed into a
time period of just 7 years. She argues
that the only thing that stretches it
out to a much longer period is this
passage in Galatians in which Paul
describes his conversion and then writes
afterwards I went into Arabia. Later I
returned to Damascus. Then after 3 years
I went up to Jerusalem. Then I went to
Syria and Cissia. Then after 14 years I
went up again to Jerusalem. Now, it's
unclear as to whether that 14 years was
after the 3 years or whether it was 14
years total, but either way, this
triples the total length of his
ministry, even though nowhere in the New
Testament does it describe what he did
during those 14 years, which is kind of
strange. Therefore, Einhorn argues that
the 14 years was actually a later
addition and that the entirety of Paul's
ministry, including his seven genuine
letters, can in fact be placed after the
Egyptians revolt. But there's still a
major problem because there is one
particular date in Paul's life that can
be pinpointed with almost 100% accuracy.
You see in Acts 18 it mentions that Paul
was taken to court in Corenth during the
tenure of a Roman governor named
Gallalo. We know from Roman records when
Gallalio served and therefore we can
date that incident to exactly 51 CE.
This definitely places Paul in Corenth
before the Egyptians revolt in
Jerusalem. So unless one argues that the
Gallio reference was yet another thing
that was added later, Einhorn's whole
time shift theory basically falls apart.
[music]
The third theory we'll be looking at was
developed by a retired accountant named
Daniel Unbrink and it is presented in
his book Judas of Nazareth. In this
book, Hunterbrink argues that Jesus was
the exact same person as the historical
figure Judas of Galilee, who I mentioned
last time as being the one who led the
census revolt of 6 CE. Okay, let me now
tell you about Judas of Galilee and his
potential connection to Jesus. This
time, I'm going to build a timeline
based on Josephus. Now, in case you
don't know who Josephus is, well, he was
a Jewish Roman historian who lived about
a generation or two after Jesus. His two
main books, Antiquities of the Jews and
the Jewish War, both of which were
written in Greek, are the best secular
sources we have for what was happening
in First Century Judea. So, let me start
by adding some of the events we talked
about in the first two episodes to the
timeline. In episode 1, I mentioned that
Herod the Great kills his second and
thirdborn sons Alexander and Aristobulus
in 7 B.CE and then his firstborn son
Antipedater in 4 B.CE. So these are the
references in Josephus to these two
events as well as the dates. Take note
that for example 16 117 means volume 16
11:7. I also talked about how Herod dies
just a few days after he kills Antiper
at which point he is succeeded by his
son Archelaus.
Now in episode 2 I mentioned that
Archelaus was eventually deposed in 6 CE
which is when Judea was made into a
Roman province to be ruled by governors
instead. This lasted until 41 CE, which
is when the Herodian monarchy was
briefly restored with Herod the Great's
grandson, Agrippa, being made king. But
Agria died after just 3 years from being
poisoned, an event that's actually
recorded in the Bible as well. Last time
I gave the wrong reference for that.
It's actually Acts 12 21-23. After this,
Judea went back to having Roman
governors. And it was during this period
that the Egyptian appeared. He's the
person who was the focus of episode 2.
But in this episode, I want to go back
to 6 CE. Remember, the first thing that
the Romans did when they took over Judea
was conduct a census so that they could
figure out how much tax revenue they
could get. Josephus mentions that census
here. And in fact, the Bible mentions it
as well. The person in charge of that
census was Quirinius who was the
governor of the next door province of
Syria. As I mentioned last time, this
led to a major rebellion led by the man
who is the focus of this episode, Judas
of Galilee. But according to Daniel
Underbrink, this is not when Judas's
story begins. You see, it's possible
that Judas of Galile's involvement in
acts of rebellion actually started much
earlier. If we go back to 4 B.CE, right
around the time of Herod the Great's
death, we get these references in
Josephus. I'll read you the one from
antiquities. There was one Judas, the
son of Saraphas. Note that this was an
alternate spelling of Sepharus, which
was a major town in Galilee, and Matias,
the son of Margolothus, two of the most
eloquent men among the Jews and the most
celebrated interpreters of Jewish laws
and men well-beloved by the people. Now,
it's not clear whether or not this Judas
is the same Judas who later led the
census revolt, but there's good reason
to assume that they are. Not only are
they both named Judas, they are both
from Galilee, are both teachers of the
law, are both popular with the people,
and are both involved in similar acts of
rebellion. Josephus goes on to write,
"The king," meaning Herod the Great, had
erected over the great gate of the
temple a large golden eagle of great
value. Now the law forbids those that
propose to live according to it to erect
images or representations of any living
creature. So these wise men Judas and
Matias persuaded their followers to pull
down the golden eagle. So in the very
middle of the day they got upon the
place they pulled down the eagle and cut
it into pieces with axes. Now what do
you think Herod thought of these
actions? Well, he of course was enraged
and had both Judas and Matias arrested.
Interestingly though, Josephus mentions
Matias being put to death, but not
Judas. This may have been because Herod
died shortly thereafter. Also
interesting is the fact that according
to Josephus, one of the first things
that Archelaus does as the new ruler is
release his father's prisoners at the
request of the people. So, it's possible
that Judas was set free at this point,
an event quite similar to the one where
Pilate releases Barabus. Josephus then
mentions a rebel named Judas again here,
this time in connection to an event that
takes place in Sepharus Galilee in which
Judas and a bunch of rebels steal
weapons from the royal palace. Again,
this may or may not be the same Judas,
but it is quite likely, especially
considering the repeated mention of
Sephus. Interestingly, yet again,
there's no mention of Judas being
killed, which means that he was still
alive to lead the census revolt in 6 CE,
which is the main event that Judas of
Galilee is associated with. Now, even
though that revolt was put down,
Josephus considers it to be a major
turning point in Judeian history because
it birthed what he calls the fourth
philosophy. The other three being the
Pharisees, Sadducees, and Essenes. The
followers of this fourth philosophy
would go on to become known as the
Zealots and or the Sakari. Terms that,
as I mentioned last time, also come up
in connection to Jesus. About two
generations after Judas of Galilee, it
would be the Zealots who would fight
against the Romans in the first Jewish
Roman war, which of course is the main
topic of Josephus's book, The Jewish
War. As you probably know, the Jews lost
that war, resulting in the complete
destruction of Jerusalem and its temple.
That in turn played a major role in the
growth of Christianity. Now, not only
was Judas of Galilee the founder of the
fourth philosophy, aka the Zealots, it
was his sons and grandsons who continued
on as the leaders of the movement. For
example, here Josephus mentions Judas's
sons, James and Simon, who led a revolt
in the 40s that was quashed by the Roman
governor at the time, Tiberius
Alexander. Then at the very start of the
war in 66 CE, Menahm, who Josephus calls
Judas's son, but was more likely his
grandson, was able to break into the
fortress of Msada, where he stole
weapons. Sound familiar? Which then
allowed him to capture Jerusalem. At
this point, Menah started to behave like
a king, which angered other zealots
because the whole point of the rebellion
was to get rid of tyrants, not to
appoint a new one. Thus, Menah ended up
being killed by his own cousin, Eliser.
It was Eliser, probably another grandson
of Judas of Galilee, who ended up being
the leader of the last Jewish holdouts
at Msada, the ones who supposedly
committed mass suicide rather than be
defeated. I say supposedly because
there's actually some debate about what
actually happened at Msada and whether
or not the rebels there should be
thought of as heroes. Now, I tell you
all of this history to drive home just
how important Judas of Galilee is in
terms of the overall history of first
century Judea and therefore how he might
have become a powerful symbol in the
minds of Jews at the time. But there's
something puzzling about Josephus's
coverage of Judas and his family.
Josephus goes out of his way to clearly
mention the deaths of four of Judas's
descendants, James, Simon, Mahm, and
Eleazar. But he does [clears throat] not
mention the death of Judas himself,
which is strange because Josephus
obviously sees Judas of Galilee and the
fourth philosophy as a central thread in
the story he's telling. And this is one
of the reasons why Daniel Underbrink
thinks that Jesus and Judas might have
been the same person. Josephus, after
discussing the census revolt and the
four main sects of Judaism, says very
little about anything that happened
during the next 20 years. The first
Judeian governor that he talks about at
length is Pontius Pilate, who he says
angered the Jews by putting up images of
Caesar and using temple funds to build
an aqueduct. It is right after this that
we get the most famous paragraph in the
entire works of Josephus, the one that
mentions Jesus. Now, according to most
scholars, the original passage was
likely altered by later Christian
scribes, but the consensus is that at
least some of the passage was in fact
written by Josephus. Here's what the
original might have looked like. About
this time there lived Jesus, a wise man,
for he was one who performed surprising
deeds and was a teacher of such people
as accept the truth gladly. He won over
many Jews and many of the Greeks. And
when upon accusation of the principal
men among us, Pilate had condemned him
to a cross, those who had first come to
love him did not cease. Now, it's not
hard to imagine that if Judas of Galilee
was still alive, he probably would have
objected to Pilate putting up images of
Caesar like he did when Herod put up the
golden eagle. And it's not hard to
imagine that this might have got him
into trouble yet again. The mention of
Jesus in the flow of Josephus's
narrative seems abrupt and out of place,
but it would fit very nicely if it was
actually a record of Judas of Galile's
death. You see, maybe the original
passage read about this time there still
lived Judas, a wise man. That would fit
much better. Remember, Josephus has
already referred to Judas as a wise man,
a term that he uses very sparingly. The
name Jesus could also have been Judas's
nickname. After all, Jesus simply means
God's savior. And it's not hard to
imagine a famous teacher revolutionary
like Judas of Galilee being thought of
as the nation's savior. But it's not
just the placement of Jesus within
Josephus's narrative that makes
Underbrink put forward the idea that
Jesus and Judas might have been the same
person. In his book, he lists 42
similarities between the two men. To be
honest, I find some of them to be a bit
of a stretch, but let me highlight a few
that do stand out. First, there's the
obvious one, the fact that both men are
from Galilee. Specifically, Jesus is
said to have come from Nazareth. And
where is Nazareth? Well, it's right next
to the much larger city of Sepharus.
Then there's the fact that there are a
lot of similarities in what they taught.
Both the fourth philosophy as well as
the early Christian movement put an
emphasis on the sharing of wealth and on
not just following the letter of the law
but on understanding its deeper meaning
which involved things like helping the
poor and fighting for justice. Both
Judas and Jesus also opposed the paying
of taxes. While most people just
remember the render unto Caesar what is
Caesar's verse, the Bible also states in
Luke 23:2 that one of the reasons why
Jesus was arrested was for opposing the
tax. There's also lots of little stuff
like the fact that Judas had two sons
named James and Simon and Jesus had two
brothers named James and Simon. Judas
had followers called Zealots and Jesus
had followers called Zealots. Now, some
of the arguments that Hunterbrink uses
are actually based on a different
version of Josephus known as the Savonic
Josephus. I haven't used any of these
references so far. The Savonic Josephus
is based on a manuscript that dates to
1463, which was likely based on a
translation of Josephus made a few
centuries earlier in Keieven Roose. The
thing is, it's quite a bit different
from the standard Josephus with lots of
stuff omitted and some other stuff
added. So, it's unclear whether the
Savonic Josephus represents something
closer to the original or whether it's a
later Christian creation. Most scholars
lean toward it being not authentic,
whereas underbrink leans toward it being
authentic. One of his arguments is based
on the placement of John the Baptist in
the Savonic Josephus. The standard
Josephus places John the Baptist here
close to the mention of Jesus, whereas
the savonic Josephus places him here,
right before Judas of Galilee and the
census revolt. That seems like a strange
thing for a Christian scribe to do on
purpose because it contradicts the
biblical account. Antbrink therefore
argues that this is in fact the original
version and that therefore John the
Baptist is quite clearly linked to Judas
of Galilee. He also points out that the
savonic Josephus includes a story about
the star of Bethlehem, very similar to
the gospel version, but it places it
much earlier, more than 20 years before
when the gospels say Jesus was born, but
in what would likely be around the time
when Judas of Galilee was born. Which
brings me to the question of why then
did the gospel writers instead place
Jesus's birth either around the time of
Herod's death or around the time of the
census revolt? Well, according to
Unterbrinks theory, it's because these
are the two main starting points for
Judas of Galilee. The first being when
he helped tear down the Golden Eagle and
the second being when he led the census
revolt. In other words, these are
symbolic births, not literal ones. Now,
I think the greatest weakness in
Underbrink's book is that he makes too
many assumptions, such as linking all of
Josephus's Judas's together when Judas
was one of the most popular names at the
time, as well as his reliance on the
Savonic Josephus, which most scholars
don't accept as being genuine. Well, one
thing that I do really like about
Unterbrink's book is that he shows in a
step-by-step fashion how a historical
Jewish movement led by an ordinary man
might have eventually evolved into the
religion we now know as Christianity. In
other words, even if Judas of Galilee
wasn't Jesus, the standard secular view
is that some first century character was
and that that character eventually
morphed into the Jesus of the New
Testament based on how his followers
viewed him after his death. Here's how
Unbrink explains it. Originally, there
was some sort of very Jewish movement
around a guy called Jesus. It was very
Jewish in the sense that it was mostly
made up of Jews, and it's still promoted
following Jewish laws such as
circumcision and the kosher rules. You
can still see traces of this original
movement in how the New Testament
portrays James and Peter. But then at
some point, Paul arrives on the scene
and Paul starts focusing more on gaining
gentile converts. This involves dropping
the adherence to Jewish laws and instead
universalizing and spiritualizing the
message so that Jesus is now seen as the
Messiah of all mankind. Paul doesn't
write the four gospels, but he has a
strong influence over those that did.
Then following the destruction of
Jerusalem and the temple, Paul's
movement suddenly makes more sense than
the original one. The Gospels get
written, turning Jesus into more of a
legend. And eventually the movement
evolves into what we know today as
Christianity.
It's called [music] the Flavian
hypothesis and it's mostly based on the
book Caesar's Messiah by Joseph Atwell
published in 2005. Basically, the idea
is that the Romans invented Christianity
shortly after they destroyed Jerusalem
in 70 CE and that the character of Jesus
is really just a disguise for Emperor
Titus, who was the one who defeated the
Jews. Let me start by reminding you who
the Roman emperors were during the
lifetime of Jesus, as well as during the
first several decades of Christianity.
To do this, I'll use our Roman Emperor's
family tree chart, which of course is
available from usefulcharts.com.
When Jesus was born, the Roman Empire
was still in its infancy, and therefore
its very first emperor, Augustus Caesar,
was still in charge. However, around the
time that Jesus would have been a
teenager, Augustus, died and was
succeeded by his adopted son, Tiberius.
It was therefore Tiberius who was the
emperor during the entire length of
Jesus's ministry as well as at the time
of the crucifixion. Tiberius was then
followed by three of his relatives,
Caligula, Claudius, and Nero. These
three served during the days of the
earliest apostles such as Peter and
Paul. But then in the year 68, which is
when Nero died, this original line of
emperors known as the Julioclaudians
came to an end. What followed was a
brief civil war in ' 69 known as the
year of the four emperors which ended
when Vespasian became emperor. At this
point a new imperial dynasty was formed
known as the Flavians. Now interestingly
when Vespasian was declared emperor he
was actually in Judea leading the Roman
armies in the first Jewish Roman war. So
he had to quickly depart for Rome and
leave his son Titus in charge of
finishing the war against the Jews,
which Titus did, destroying Jerusalem in
70 CE. 9 years later, when Vespasian
died, it was Titus who became the next
emperor. So whether or not the Flavian
hypothesis is true, it is an undisputed
fact that both Vespasian and Titus have
a strong connection to Judea. On top of
this, according to most mainstream
scholars, it was also during the reigns
of Vespasian and Titus that the earliest
of the four canonical gospels, Mark, was
likely written. So that puts the
Flavians in charge at the exact moment
when the story of Jesus was being
recorded for the very first time. And
here's the thing, in light of what we
know about Judeian history at the time,
the story of Jesus is kind of strange.
As we've seen in the last two episodes,
Judea was a hotbed of anti-Roman
activity. Because the monotheistic
religion of Judaism was incompatible
with the polytheism of the empire, there
were constant revolts and rebellions
with lots of would-be Jewish heroes
repeatedly trying to overthrow the
Romans and regain Judeian independence.
But although there are hints throughout
the gospel that Jesus and his disciples
had links to rebel groups, the gospels
are for the most part very pro- Roman
and pro- pacifism. For example, Jesus is
quoted as saying things like, "Render
unto Caesar the things that are Caesars.
Do not resist evil. Whoever slaps you on
your right cheek, turn to him the other
cheek also. And even love your enemies.
Pray for those who persecute you. On top
of this, Roman soldiers and tax
collectors for the Romans are often
portrayed in a positive light. In Luke
7, Jesus heals the servant of a Roman
centurion and then says of the soldier,
"I tell you, not even in Israel have I
found such faith." Later in Acts, which
was written by the same author, another
Roman centurion named Cornelius becomes
one of the first gentile converts to
Christianity. As for tax collectors,
there's the story of Zakias, who is
portrayed as being righteous because he
climbs a tree to see Jesus, and Levi,
aka Matthew, who becomes one of the 12
disciples. In contrast, the Jewish
leaders are consistently portrayed as
being the bad guys. So, ironically,
after decades of anti-Roman activity in
Judea, we suddenly get a new movement
that is quite openly pro- Roman or at
least neutral towards the Romans, being
focused on spiritual matters rather than
political ones. So, even if the Flavians
didn't invent Christianity, they
definitely would have seen it as being a
positive development, especially
compared to the previous Jewish
movements which had been so troublesome.
This new Christian form of Judaism
didn't even require its followers to
adhere to all those strange Jewish
customs like circumcision and avoiding
pork. In other words, in the very
henistic world of the Roman Empire,
Christianity fit in much better than
Judaism. So beyond the fact that the
reigns of the Flavians perfectly overlap
with the writing of the gospels and that
the gospels are quite favorable towards
Rome, what evidence is there that the
Flavians might actually have been
involved in creating this new religion?
Well, first of all, according to
tradition, it is thought that several
members of the Flavian family might have
been Christians. Most important is
Titus's niece Damatillaa who is
considered a saint by both the Catholic
and Greek Orthodox churches. She is
associated with the catacombs of
Damatillaa which includes some of the
earliest images we have of Jesus. She
was married to her second cousin,
Clemens, who Adwell claims was the same
person as Clement of Rome, the fourth or
perhaps even the second pope as well as
the author of the first epistle of
Clement. However, Atwell's main evidence
for the Flavians being the creators of
Christianity are the parallels that he
sees between several stories about Jesus
recorded in the Gospels and certain
military battles fought by Titus
recorded in Josephus. He even goes as
far as to claim that Jesus is simply
Titus in disguise created in order to
trick the Jews into worshiping Titus as
a god. For example, there's the story of
Jesus calling the first disciples on the
shores of the Sea of Galilee. There he
says to Peter and Andrew, "Follow me and
I will make you fishers of men." Atwell
argues that this is an illusion to a
famous battle fought at the exact same
location during the early phase of the
Jewish Roman war. In book 3, chapter 10
of the Jewish War, Josephus describes a
scene where Titus and his soldiers end
up stabbing the Jewish rebels in the
water with long spears as if they were
literally fishing for men. Then there's
the story that takes place near the city
of Gdora in which Jesus casts out a
legion of demons from a madman and then
allows them to enter a herd of pigs at
which point they race off the side of a
cliff and are drowned. Once again, there
was a battle that occurred at this same
spot during the Jewish Roman War. In
book four, chapter 7 of the Jewish War,
Josephus describes that the Jewish
rebels rushed at the Roman soldiers like
the wildest of wild beasts only to then
rush to their own deaths. Atwell goes on
to show many other parallels in his
book, but I think you get the point. Oh,
and did I mention that Josephus himself
was a Flavian, too? Well, he was kind of
supposedly Josephus predicted that
Vespasian would become emperor and
therefore when he did, Vespasian took
him into his household and sort of
adopted him, allowing him to use the
name Flavius. The idea here is that
because Josephus was connected to the
Flavians, he was able to make sure his
account and the gospel account lined up
perfectly. The best example of the
Gospels and Josephus lining up perfectly
is Jesus's prophecy of Jerusalem's
destruction. In Mark 13:1, Jesus says,
"Do you see these great buildings? Not
one stone will be left here upon
another. All will be thrown down." And
then in verse 30, he says, "Truly I tell
you, this generation will not pass away
until all these things have taken
place." Scholars best guess as to when
Jesus said this is 30 CE, right before
he died. And according to Josephus, the
temple was destroyed in 70 CE. That's
exactly 40 years, which also happens to
be what Jewish literature at the time
considered to be the average length of
one generation. In other words, Jesus
was spoton. So either Jesus did in fact
prophesy things correctly or whoever
wrote the gospels made it seem as if he
did. Atwell of course argues for the
latter. His argument is that Titus saw
himself as the Jewish Messiah and the
culmination of Jewish history. He points
out that in the early parts of the
gospel story, there are clear parallels
to the overall narrative of the Hebrew
Bible. Parallels that any Jew at the
time would have seen. First, a guy named
Joseph goes down to Egypt. Next, there
is a massacre of young children. Then,
there is a return to God's promised land
where there is a symbolic cleansing with
water. Finally, there is a period of
either 40 years or 40 days in the
wilderness. So yeah, the idea is that
the next chapter of Jewish history will
be like the first, except this time
their new future will involve being
ruled by the glorious Roman emperors who
will be their new gods, especially
Titus, who was the son of the father, V,
the Spasian. Now, the last piece of
evidence for this theory comes not from
Atwell, but from the authors of the 2018
book, Creating Christ. This newer book
claims to provide actual archaeological
evidence for the Flavian hypothesis.
Their argument mostly rests on this
symbol here seen on the back of a coin
with Vespasian's image. According to the
authors, this exact symbol was used by
early Christians as demonstrated by
these carvings found in Christian
catacombs as well as these rings, some
of which have text which proves that
they were indeed used by Christians. We
also know that this symbol is associated
with the Latin phrase Vistina Lente
which means make haste slowly which was
the motto of Emperor Titus. Okay, so all
of this seems on the surface at least
very interesting but there are some
major problems with the hypothesis. The
biggest one in my mind is the fact that
there was simply no need for the Flavian
emperors to go through all the trouble
of creating a new religion for the Jews
when they had already defeated them
militarily. And I mean like really
defeated them. Jerusalem was totally
destroyed in 70 CE. So by the time Titus
became emperor in 79, the Jews were a
distant memory for him. Plus, he had
other stuff to worry about. Just two
months into his reign, Mount Vuvius
erupted, destroying the city of Pompei.
And then the following year, fire broke
out in Rome, destroying several
important buildings. Plus, he had to
finish the massive coliseum project that
his father had started. So, I doubt he
had much time to care about whether or
not the Jews thought of him as their
Messiah. Plus, there's the fact that the
Gospels don't seem anywhere near
coordinated enough to have been a
governmentsponsored project backed by
the emperors. Sure, Matthew and Luke
definitely copied Mark, but what about
the dozens of other gospels that didn't
make it into the canon, and the fact
that the Greek used in the Gospels is
very different from the Greek used by
Josephus. But here's the thing. While
many of the theories we've been
discussing come across as trying to
hammer a square peg into a round hole,
they often do end up conveying some good
ideas if you look at the general points
rather than the specifics. For example,
last time I mentioned that even if it's
a stretch to say that Judas of Galilee
was the exact same person as Jesus, the
general idea of some first century
Jewish teacher slowly morphing into the
character we all know as Jesus is in
fact quite plausible. Well, the same
goes for the Flavian hypothesis. Even if
the Flavian emperors didn't go out of
their way to intentionally create
Christianity, the events in Judea that
they were involved with certainly did
play a role. You see, after the
destruction of Jerusalem in 70 CE, all
hope of creating an independent Jewish
state was pretty much lost. Therefore,
Jewish groups that were more pacifist
and willing to live alongside the
Romans, like Christianity, suddenly
became more dominant. Christianity had
the added bonus of making it easy for
Gentiles to join. So, it was perhaps no
surprise that the Christian version of
Judaism eventually eclipsed all the
other versions. So the bottom line is
the Roman Empire under the Flavians was
a much better environment for
Christianity to flourish in than was the
Roman Empire under the Julio Colaudians.
Now before I go, I do want to mention
that there are several other theories
related to the Flavian hypothesis that I
won't be covering because they're so
similar. For example, there's this book
that claims that the Jesus story was
actually a retelling of Julius Caesar's
life. And this one that claims that the
wealthy Piso family created
Christianity. However, the most
interesting book related to this theory
is perhaps this one by Russian author
Kurill Yescov. In English, it's called
The Gospel of Aphronius. and it includes
a short novel about a Roman soldier
named Aphronas who is the head of
Ponteus Pilot's secret service. In this
fictional world, Aphronas manages to
manipulate Jesus and his disciples and
turn their movement into one that serves
the needs of Rome.
>> [music]
>> Well, today I'm finally going to address
one of the most shocking hypotheses of
all, the one that holds that Jesus never
actually existed. Okay, so first of all,
let's make a timeline of the earliest
sources we have for Jesus, including the
Bible. As I've mentioned before, there
are seven Pauline epistles that
virtually all scholars agree on as being
genuinely written by Paul. These were
written from around 50 to 65 CE and are
the absolute earliest texts that we have
that mention Jesus. But take note that
they were not written by an eyewitness
of Jesus's life, but rather by someone
who joined the Christian movement after
Jesus died. Next comes the Gospel of
Mark, which was likely written around 70
CE, probably after Jerusalem was
destroyed by the Romans. Then we get
Matthew in the 80s, Luke Acts in the
'90s, and finally John, probably no
earlier than 100 CE. But once again,
none of these were written by an
eyewitness of Jesus's life. That's
because according to most scholars, the
four gospels were not actually written
by Matthew, Mark, Luke, and John. They
were just named after those four
individuals. As for the rest of the New
Testament, as well as the earliest texts
written by the early church fathers,
none of those predate the destruction of
the temple, and most date to the second
century rather than the first. So, we
have nothing written by anyone who knew
Jesus personally. And other than the
seven letters written by Paul, nothing
from his own generation. Let's now add
the earliest non-biblical sources that
we have. The earliest of all would be
the passage from Josephus that I
mentioned in episode 3. It dates to 93
CE. And although it was likely
embellished later, it does seem to have
a core that is genuine. After this,
there's brief mentions by Plenny the
Younger in 110, Tacitus in 116,
Swatonius in 121, and an illusion made
to him by a stoic philosopher named Mara
Bar Serapion, which is difficult to
date, but likely falls around the same
time as these other four. Now, without
knowing anything else, this looks like
some pretty solid evidence, especially
considering that Jesus was just some guy
from a rural area. But let's now go back
and examine each source more closely,
starting with Paul. There is something
really strange about the writings of
Paul that the average person usually
never notices until it's pointed out to
them. and that is that Paul never
mentions even in passing any of the key
details about Jesus's earthly life such
as that he had a mother named Mary or
that he came from a town called
Nazareth. Even more surprising is that
there's not a single mention of any of
his miracles or any of his healings. On
top of this, there's not a single quote
from any of Jesus's parables or any of
his sermons. Lots of things that Jesus
said are recorded in the four gospels.
So obviously records of his teachings
were floating around either orally or in
now lost documents such as the Q source.
You'd think that Paul would have at
least once referenced something that
Jesus said prior to his final week in
order to make some sort of point or at
least once referenced one of Jesus's
miracles in order to prove that Jesus
was divine. But he does not. He does
mention James whom he calls brother of
the Lord, but it's unclear whether he
means literal brother or brother in
Christ, a term used to mean fellow
Christian. So the earliest reference we
have to any historical details about
Jesus's life is actually Mark. But even
then, we don't get a birth narrative and
we don't even get any postresurrection
appearances either. Mark simply ends
with the empty tomb. Matthew then copies
Mark extensively and adds some more
details, but it's really only when we
get to the author of Luke that we
finally get someone who claims to be
writing a careful historical account a
full 60 plus years after the events in
question. As for the extra biblical
sources, well, other than Josephus, they
all mention Christ, which is a title,
rather than Jesus, which is a personal
name, or they simply just mention
Christians in general. Swatonius doesn't
even get his spelling right using Cresto
instead of Christrist. So here's how
Richard Carrier interprets all of this
in the same manner that Muhammad claimed
to have heard the voice of a spiritual
being named Gabriel and Joseph Smith
claimed to have heard the voice of a
spiritual being named Moroni. Perhaps
what really happened is that Peter one
day claimed to have heard the voice of a
spiritual being named Jesus. And then
other apostles claimed to have heard it
too, including after a few years a
famous Pharisee named Paul. Perhaps the
idea that Jesus was a historical person
developed only after a generation or two
had passed when no one was still around
who could say otherwise. This would
certainly explain why Paul never
mentions any historical details about
Jesus's life. and only seems to know
about a very mystical Jesus who appears
to him in dreams and visions. We do know
that first century Jews did in fact
believe in all sorts of lesser spiritual
beings. Satan being a good example. They
adopted him from Zoroastrianism. We also
know from books like Ezekiel and Daniel
that the Jews in those days also
believed that there was an entire spirit
world where events that happened there
could have an impact on events that
happened down here on Earth. This is why
Carrier uses the term outer space in
reference to Jesus. He's not saying that
Jesus was an alien like the kind
depicted in modern movies, but rather
that Jesus was originally believed to be
an invisible spiritual being equivalent
to others like Satan, Gabriel, and
Michael, which is exactly what several
so-called heretical groups such as the
Aryans did in fact believe well into the
7th century. But whereas Aryanism taught
that Jesus was a created spiritual being
who did in fact come down and die a
literal death on earth, Carrier's
hypothesis is that the original
Christians actually believed that his
descent as well as his death all took
place in the invisible spirit realm aka
outer space. Basically, the idea was
that Jesus, who was the highest ranking
out of all the created spiritual beings,
tricked Satan, the main bad guy in the
spirit world, into killing him by means
of a cosmic crucifixion. And that by
doing so, he, meaning Jesus, ended up
paying for the sins of humanity and thus
became God's savior, which is why he
ends up being called Jesus, which
literally means God's savior. Now, that
all might sound crazy to us today, but
it wouldn't have to the people living in
the early Roman Empire. After all, this
story fits perfectly alongside other
stories from the ancient world, such as
the myths told by the Greeks or the ones
told by the Egyptians. The only
difference is that the cosmic Jesus
story has a Jewish spin to it. In
particular, there was a certain type of
ancient religion that was growing in
popularity around the time that
Christianity was born, that of personal
salvation cults. These new movements
were all about providing followers the
guarantee of a good place in the
afterlife and were religions you had to
join rather than be born into. They were
usually open to anyone regardless of
ethnicity or social class and had
special joining ceremonies similar to
baptism. Once you were initiated, you
called other members, brothers and
sisters, and had special meals where you
reenacted the presence of your central
spiritual figure who was usually the son
or daughter of the supreme god. H sounds
a lot like early Christianity. In other
ancient Mediterranean religions,
mythological characters were often given
biographies, making it seem as if they
were real historical figures. In
Carrier's view, this is what happened
with Jesus. Starting with the more loose
account given in Mark and
[clears throat] building up to the more
historically sounding account given in
Luke Acts. In order to measure how
likely it is that the gospels are simply
myths, he introduces the rank raglin
scale which was developed in the 20th
century in order to help distinguish
between mythical figures and historical
ones. The scale consists of a list of 22
features that are often found in ancient
writings about heroes. The more features
that apply to the person in question,
the more likely it is that that person
is mythological. So, for example,
Heracles scores 18, whereas Alexander
the Great scores seven. If you'd prefer
a comparison from the Hebrew Bible,
well, Moses scores 20, whereas Ezra
scores seven. So, what is Jesus's score?
Well, like Moses, he's a solid 20. Now,
the standard explanation for this given
by most non-Christian scholars is that
nearly all of the details we have about
Jesus's life are in fact legends and
embellishments added later on top of who
the historical Jesus actually was. Well,
what Carrier argues is if we already
admit most of it is myth and legend, why
not all of it? Okay, let's now shift
gears and take a look at why most
non-Christian scholars, myself included,
reject the mythicist hypothesis and
instead hold that Jesus did in fact
exist, even if he didn't do stuff like
heal the blind and raise the dead. In
terms of sources, I'll be relying
heavily on this book for the second part
of the video. Did Jesus exist? The
historical argument for Jesus of
Nazareth by Bartman. If you wanted to
read just one book on the topic of the
historical Jesus, I would highly
recommend that you read this one. Let me
point out that the relationship between
myth and history usually progresses in
the way that is famously described by
Galadriel in Lord of the Rings. At the
very beginning of the first movie, she
says, "History becomes legend. Legend
becomes myth." Now, although Galadriel
is a fictional character, what she says
here is absolutely true. There are
countless examples throughout history of
real people who were later turned into
more legendary characters. So much so
that if they were able to travel forward
into time, they wouldn't even recognize
themselves. people such as Gilgamesh,
Emoteep, Seamuramas, Criesus, and even
more recent people like McBth, Vlad the
Impaler, and Blackbeard the pirate. Even
characters like King Arthur, Helen of
Troy, and Moses were likely each based
off of some distant person, or perhaps
persons who were real, even if they
originally had different names and very
different lives. But whereas it's common
for history to turn into myth and
legend, sometimes quite quickly, it
rarely goes in the other direction. That
would be like a subset of Mormons
suddenly claiming that the angel Moroni
was a real historical person who was
actually Joseph Smith's nextdoor
neighbor. So, the fact that the Gospels
include all sorts of extra stuff not
found in Paul, stuff that sounds a lot
like myth and legend, well, that's not
really much of a surprise because real
people get mythologized all the time. If
Jesus's existence was 100% made up and
the whole thing started with just
visions and dreams, well, the evidence
for that would look quite a bit
different. Let's start with Paul. Sure,
he doesn't mention a lot of details, but
he does actually mention some. In fact,
he mentions some pretty important ones
which make it clear that he believed
that Jesus was a real human guy. Take
for example Galatians 4:4 where Paul
writes, "But when the fullness of time
had come, God sent his son born of a
woman born under the law." So sure, Mary
isn't mentioned by name, but Paul quite
clearly says that Jesus was born of a
woman. That's not something that is ever
said of any spiritual being in Jewish
thought, such as Satan, Gabriel, or
Michael. Only humans are born of a
woman. Paul also says that Jesus was
born under the law. That's his way of
saying that Jesus was like him, born as
a Jew. To be a Jew, one has to be a
human. Spiritual beings are neither Jew
nor Gentile. Only humans get those
labels. Finally, there's the fact that
Paul also several times mentions the
blood of Jesus. Blood is a very physical
human thing. Once again, it's never used
in Jewish thought when talking about
spiritual beings. Let's now talk about
the Gospels. Although the first one,
Mark, was written about 40 years after
Jesus died, it's quite clear that the
author did not create the entire thing
out of his own imagination. In other
words, the belief that Jesus had been a
historical person already existed by 70
CE and must have existed for some time
because by the time the author of Mark
sat down to write his gospel, there were
already certain texts and traditions in
place about the human Jesus that he was
able to use. And I'm not just referring
to collections of Jesus's sayings in
Greek, such as the hypothetical Q
source. It appears that Mark also relied
on certain oral traditions in Aramaic or
perhaps even some Aramaic documents. We
know this because some of the Aramaic is
still present in the text. One example
that Bartman uses is Mark 5 where Jesus
says in Aramaic Talithum, meaning little
girl, get up. which Mark then translates
for his original readers into Greek. If
Mark was just writing the whole thing
from scratch in Greek, it seems strange
that he would add the Aramaic. But if he
were translating the story from Aramaic
into Greek, it makes sense. You keep the
exact quote in the original language for
dramatic effect. I won't go into it, but
elsewhere in Mark 2, there's something
that Jesus says in Greek that doesn't
make sense unless we translate it back
into Aramaic. Bartman's book, Did Jesus
Exist? explains this all in great
detail. So, the point is, it seems
likely that Mark was relying on earlier
Aramaic sources. So, if Paul was still
writing in the 60s, believing that Jesus
was just an invisible spirit, how is it
that the author of Mark, who wrote in
70, used toes that already existed,
which portrayed Jesus as a walking,
talking human? In other words, there
simply wasn't enough time for cosmically
crucified Jesus to morph into walking
around Judea Jesus. There's also the
fact that the gospels are just too
messy. What I mean by this is that they
don't read like they're from a movement
that had just recently decided to make a
story from scratch about how a certain
spiritual being that they all believed
in had actually been a real human. How
they read is like the authors are trying
to sew together a bunch of contradicting
legends and rumors about someone into a
single coherent narrative. You see,
there's some stuff in the gospel
narratives that don't make a lot of
sense unless they're there because they
have to be there because they actually
happened. You see, you can always add
stuff to a story to make it seem better,
but it's pretty hard to remove certain
details if they're details that people
already know about. Like, if someone
wanted to create a fictional story about
a magical US president, they probably
wouldn't invent a scenario in which he
lost to someone else between his two
terms. But if 50 years from now someone
was writing a story about Donald Trump,
even if they claimed that Trump had
magical powers, they'd have to leave in
the part about him losing to Joe Biden
because, well, that really did happen.
This is called the criteria of
embarrassment. And in Jesus's case, it
can be applied to the role played by
John the Baptist. You see, in Matthew,
Mark, and Luke, Jesus gets baptized by
John the Baptist. something that seems a
bit strange from the perspective of
Christian theology. You see, for
Christians, Jesus is God and therefore
obviously superior to John. So, how
could John perform a sacrament like
baptism for Jesus being that a sacrament
is an act that imparts divine grace? The
point is, this doesn't seem like
something that someone writing a myth
from scratch would put in. However, if
it really did happen and people knew
about it, whoever wanted to mythologize
Jesus's life would have to work it in
somehow. Even the crucifixion itself
seems like a strange element to add to a
story. If this was all happening in the
spirit realm, wouldn't it have been
better to have Jesus die in some sort of
epic battle against Satan rather than in
a solitary rather humiliating way like
crucifixion? On the other hand, if there
really was a Jewish teacher named Jesus
who was crucified for political reasons,
it makes sense that his followers might
use that event and create a story around
it in order to keep their movement
going. So to sum up, in order for
mythicism to be true, we have to believe
that the entire passage in Josephus is
fake. That Paul definitely meant brother
as brother in Christ when referring to
James. that being born of a woman, being
born a Jew, being of the seed of David,
being crucified, shedding blood, that
all of these things can be understood in
some sort of non-physical way. And
finally, that whoever made up the story
about Jesus being historical did so
fairly quickly and decided that it was
super important for Jesus to start out
as seemingly subordinate to John the
Baptist. So, I don't know. For me, you
have to do a lot of stretching to make
that all work. When it seems much more
plausible that Jesus, like so many other
heroes throughout history, was in fact a
real person who was simply mythologized
after his death. For this reason, I
personally think that the mythsist
hypothesis fits in the same category as
most of the other hypotheses that we've
looked at. Kind of interesting to
consider, but probably not true.
There is in fact a general consensus
among scholars about who the historical
Jesus actually was. Of course, Christian
scholars say that he was God incarnate.
But what I'm talking about here is what
secular scholars have concluded. And
what most secular scholars have
concluded is that Jesus was an
apocalyptic prophet who was killed for
stirring up trouble in Jerusalem during
one of the annual Passover festivals.
These days, the leading scholar on the
historical Jesus is, in my opinion, Bart
Airman. So take note that much of what
I'll be covering today is based on his
books. in particular, Jesus, the
apocalyptic prophet of the new
millennium, and how Jesus became God,
the exaltation of a Jewish preacher from
Galilee. So, the first thing I have to
explain is what an apocalyptic prophet
is. To do that, let's go back around 750
years before Jesus and look at the role
that prophets originally played in
ancient Israel and Judah. So, this is my
timeline of biblical composition chart.
As you can see, the oldest books in the
entire Hebrew Bible are Amos, Hosea,
Micah, and Isaiah. Take note that both
Micah and Isaiah were added to later.
So, when it comes to those two, I'm
referring to the first portions of the
books only. What all four of these early
prophets have in common is that they
were writing during the time when the
northern kingdom of Israel was about to
fall to the Assyrian Empire. So their
goal was to prevent this from happening
by trying to convince the Israelites to
change their ways. But here's the
important thing. Their message was to
the nation as a whole, not to each
person individually. And their focus was
on one particular sin, not bad behavior
in general. And that one particular sin
was idolatry. So the message was stop
worshiping other gods and turn back to
the one true God, the one known by the
four letters Yhwh.
If you do that, God will help you defeat
the Assyrians. Well, we know how the
story goes. The Israelites did not
defeat the Assyrians, although the
southern kingdom of Judah did. Thus, the
worship of YHW flourished there, at
least for a while. But then a new enemy
entered the scene, the Babylonians. So
more prophets were sent again with a
similar message to the entire nation.
Stop worshiping other gods. If you turn
back to the one true god, you will
survive. But again, this didn't happen.
Judah fell to the Babylonians. Now
later, the Persians did let the
Judahites return to Jerusalem and
rebuild their temple. But even though
the Judahites, now called Jews, were
careful to worship the one true God
only, they remained under foreign rule.
Thus, the message of the prophets
started to change. To demonstrate this,
let me show you two very different
verses from the Hebrew Bible. The first
one is from Exodus 20, which is part of
a very old law code that was likely
written way back here around 750 B.CE.
It says, "You shall not bow down to
other gods or worship them, for I, the
Lord your God, am a jealous God,
punishing the children for the sin of
the parents to the third and fourth
generation." Contrast this with what was
written about 300 years later in the
book of Ezekiel around 450 B.CE. The one
who sins is the one who will die. The
child will not share the guilt of the
parent, nor will the parent share the
guilt of the child. the righteousness of
the righteous will be credited to them
and the wickedness of the wicked will be
charged against them. So, first of all,
there's a shift from national sins to
individual sins. But that's not the only
difference. In Ezekiel, as well as in
Zachchariah and Joel, we find some of
the earliest apocalyptic visions. The
word apocalyptic comes from the Greek
apocalyppsis which means an unveiling of
something hidden. So instead of prophets
talking about real physical armies that
are about to attack, they instead start
talking about invisible entities
representing good and evil that are
fighting each other in an unseen spirit
realm. You see, the idea is that
although the good guys always seem to
lose down here on Earth, that's just
because the unseen battle that is going
on upstairs hasn't yet finished. But
when it does, everything will be okay
because then the triumphant forces of
good will come down to earth and make
things right here as well. Even the
righteous dead will be resurrected. By
the time we get to Daniel, which was the
very last book in the Hebrew Bible to be
written, these ideas had been fleshed
out even more. In Daniel 7, we learned
that one like a son of man would
eventually appear in the clouds and that
this figure, with God's permission,
would then come down to earth and rule
all nations. Now, in the Hebrew Bible,
the term son of man or sons of man
occurs about 100 times. And in each
case, it always refers to a human being
or humans in general. So in other words,
the phrase son of man can basically be
swapped out for the word human. But take
note, the author of Daniel doesn't say
that a human would appear in the clouds.
He says that one like a human would. So
the idea is that some sort of spiritual
being that looks like a human, perhaps
an angel, would eventually appear. In
subsequent apocalyptic literature, this
spiritual being is simply referred to as
the son of man. And his future rule on
earth is simply referred to as the
kingdom of God. But remember, the son of
man was not God, nor was he a human. He
was something in between. Again, the
closest concept we have for such a being
is that of an angel. And we do know that
the ancient Jews did believe in angels.
So the message that an apocalyptic
prophet brings is don't worry, the evil
world that you're experiencing right now
is going to end very soon. So shape up
and be good so that when the son of man
comes, you can be part of the new
kingdom of God. Which brings us to Jesus
because a lot of what Jesus said was
along these same lines, especially when
we look at Matthew, Mark, and Luke,
which are our earliest sources as
opposed to John, which was written
later. For example, Jesus often
references this son of man character,
like in Mark, where he says, "Whoever is
ashamed of me and my words, of that
person will the son of man also be
ashamed when he comes." Now, if you're a
Christian or a former Christian, you're
probably used to assuming that whenever
Jesus refers to the Son of Man, he's
referring to himself. But if you take
his words at face value and put yourself
in the place of the people who first
heard those words, it actually makes
more sense to assume that he is talking
about someone else, a figure that
everyone was familiar with who had not
yet come. Jesus also talked a lot about
the kingdom of God. In fact, his very
first words in Mark are, "The time has
come. The kingdom of God is almost
here." A few chapters later, he's way
more specific. He says, "I tell you the
truth, there are some standing here
today who will not taste death until
they see the kingdom of God come in
power." Now, Christians are taught to
understand this as referring to Jesus's
resurrection and the giving of the Holy
Spirit. But to the people who were
listening at the time, they would
definitely have interpreted it in the
Jewish apocalyptic sense, they would
have understood it to mean that the
Romans were about to be crushed and that
the kingdom of God was about to be
established on earth within their own
lifetimes. Hence, the urgency to repent
and make changes to their life right
then and there. On top of this, all of
Jesus's actions were basically him
modeling what the soon-coming kingdom of
God was going to look like. So soon
there would be no more disease, hence
Jesus healed the sick. Soon there would
be no more war, hence Jesus encouraged
nonviolence. And soon there would be no
more poverty, hence Jesus told people to
give away their possessions in order to
help the poor. But here's the really
important one. Soon the current temple
would be replaced with a new one. Hence,
Jesus went to the temple and flipped
over a bunch of tables, creating a
scene. It was this final symbolic
gesture that likely got him in trouble.
From the Christian perspective, the
story of Jesus and the money changers at
the temple is not all that important.
It's just one of the many strange things
that Jesus did during his time on earth.
But when it comes to the historical
Jesus, it very well might be the most
important part of the story. You see,
it's included in all four gospels. Yet,
like I say, it's not really all that
central to the Christian message. In
fact, it kind of goes against how Jesus
is usually portrayed, which is very
gentle and nonviolent. Therefore, it is
very likely that this is one of the
events recorded in the Gospels that did
in fact actually happen. Now, it may
seem odd that the Romans would have
killed a guy just for flipping over some
tables. But you see, there was an
additional aspect to Jesus's teachings
that only he and his inner circle knew
about. In fact, the gospel writers make
it super clear that he wanted to keep
this part secret. And the secret was
that when the kingdom of God was
established, Jesus was going to be in
charge with his 12 disciples ruling
directly under him. Now the word used in
the gospels for Jesus being in charge is
Messiah. And here once again it's
important to put aside later notions of
what the word Messiah means and think
about what it meant in its original
context because in its original context
it simply meant anointed one or king or
ruler. So let me set the scene for you.
It's Passover week and the situation is
really tense because Jerusalem is super
crowded, especially with outoftowners
who the Romans saw as potential
troublemakers. Remember also that
Passover was literally a holiday
designed to remind the Jews of a time
when they escaped from foreign rule. So,
the Romans would definitely have been on
guard for any potential threats. Then
during this intense week, the normally
passive Jesus makes a big scene at the
temple and all of the sudden he and his
disciples are under close scrutiny. One
of the 12, Judas, gets scared and
basically rats Jesus out, telling the
authorities what Jesus had said in
secret about being a future ruler. Then
Jesus gets pulled in before Pilate
doesn't deny it. So just to be on the
safe side, Pilate has him crucified. And
that's basically who Jesus was. Just one
of many apocalyptic prophets in first
century Judea who were out there telling
people that the world as they knew it
was about to end and who got himself in
deep trouble for doing so. So how did he
go from that to being thought of as God
incarnate? Well, first of all, imagine
it from the perspective of his
followers. They like many others over
the centuries really believed that the
world was about to end and that they had
been chosen by God for a very special
purpose. Thus, instead of simply
abandoning all their deeply held beliefs
after Jesus died, they simply tweaked
them a bit. We know that it's a very
common psychological phenomenon for
people to have visions of dead loved
ones, especially in cases when the death
was very unexpected and/or traumatic. We
also know that it's a very common
psychological phenomenon for people in
tight-knit religious groups to all claim
to have had the same experience. So,
think about it from the perspective of
someone who believed in apocalyptic
Judaism. They think that the
resurrection of the dead is coming soon
and now they have a dead person, their
leader, talking to them. So, maybe he's
just the first of many to be raised from
the dead. Maybe he's the son of man
who's going to return soon to usher in
the kingdom of God. That would make
sense to them because after all, he said
he was going to be the anointed one.
Thus, the earliest form of Christianity
is born. One in which Jesus was a human
who then after death was exalted by God
to a special position in preparation for
the sooncoming apocalypse. Bart Earman
calls this early form of the religion
exaltation Christianity. And
interestingly, within the writings of
Paul, we have the traces of some very
early creeds which were most likely
originally oral creeds that quite
clearly represent this view. For
example, at the very beginning of the
Epistle to the Romans, there's a section
that stands out as being highly
structured and which uses words that
Paul does not use anywhere else. It goes
like this. Who was descended from the
seed of David according to the flesh.
Who was appointed son of God in power
according to the spirit of holiness.
Take note that there's no mention of an
empty tomb here. And no mention of Jesus
ever having existed prior to his earthly
life. Just him being appointed or
exalted after his death. And just
because it uses the phrase son of God,
that doesn't mean that whoever wrote
this thought of Jesus as being equal to
God. In fact, in those days, the term
son or sons of God was often used to
refer to angels. In fact, there is
another verse in the Pauline epistles
that makes it clear that Paul thought of
Jesus as an angel, not as God. In
Galatians 4:14,
he writes, "Though my condition was a
trial to you, you did not scorn or
despise me, but received me as an angel
of God, as Christ Jesus." Now, the
assumption made by Christians is that he
meant you treated me like an angel. No,
even better. You treated me like Jesus.
But the Greek here is actually quite
clear. It means you treated me like an
angel. an angel such as Jesus. Okay, so
the earliest form of Christianity had
Jesus simply being exalted to an
angel-like position after death so that
he could now take on the role of the Son
of Man, who would appear in the clouds
and usher in the kingdom of God. All of
which the earliest Christians still
expected would occur within their own
lifetimes. One piece of evidence for
this is the fact that Paul says in first
Thessalonians, "For the Lord himself
will come down from heaven, and the dead
in Christ will rise first. After that,
we who are still alive and are left will
be caught up together with them in the
clouds to meet the Lord in the air." So
the expectation was that some would die,
but also that some would still be living
when Jesus came back. Now, pretty
quickly, debates arose over the exact
details of who Jesus was. Some started
to think that maybe he had already been
an angel while he was here on earth.
Others thought that maybe he had been an
angel before he was born on earth. This
last idea quickly evolved into what man
calls incarnation Christianity. The idea
being that Jesus was an already existing
spiritual being who was then incarnated
into a human body. Paul in particular
liked this idea and combined it with the
idea that Jesus's death paid for our
sins. But then the author
[clears throat] of John who wrote the
very last gospel 70 plus years after the
crucifixion took things even further. He
equated Jesus with God himself. You see,
by this point, Jerusalem and its temple
had been completely destroyed, and Jesus
had quite clearly not come back.
Therefore, Christianity started to shift
away from its original apocalyptic
message and more towards its salvation
message, which now had Jesus as the
replacement for the now destroyed
temple. But don't assume that everybody
was happy with this particular version
of Christianity this early on because it
would take the new religion over 200
more years for the majority of its
leaders to finally agree on it and
several more hundred years before all
the other variations of Christianity
were stamped out. So there you have it.
That is who Jesus was according to most
secular scholars. He was an apocalyptic
prophet who taught that the world was
going to end soon. But he got himself
killed by stating that he was going to
be the ruler in the future kingdom of
God. Only later in the decades after his
death was Jesus reinterpreted to fit the
needs of those he left behind.